<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lucta Iacobi: or, A bonefire for His Maiesties double deliuerie, from the deluge in Perth, the 5. of August, 1600. And the doomesday of Britaine, the 5. of Nouember. 1605. Seene and allowed</title>
            <author>Univocè-catholicus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856230</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21759</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21759)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 740:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lucta Iacobi: or, A bonefire for His Maiesties double deliuerie, from the deluge in Perth, the 5. of August, 1600. And the doomesday of Britaine, the 5. of Nouember. 1605. Seene and allowed</title>
                  <author>Univocè-catholicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for William Welby, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Churchyard, at the signe of the Gray-hound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Vniuocè-catholicus.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The diluge of Perth, and the doomesday of Britaine.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625.</term>
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LVCTA IACOBI: <hi>OR,</hi> A BONEFIRE FOR HIS MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Double Deliuerie, from the Deluge in PERTH, <hi>the</hi> 5. <hi>of August,</hi> 1600. <hi>And the Doomeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> of BRITAINE, the 5. of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1605.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. 10.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought, &amp;c: for the foule of the heauen ſhall carrie the voyce, and that which hath wings ſhall declare the matter.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Serò ſed ſeriò.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>William Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Churchyard, at the ſigne of the Gray-hound. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST happie Prince, IAMES the firſt, by the grace of God, King of Great <hi>Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Maieſties moſt bleſſed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery by the power of God from that bloodie <hi>Diluge</hi> of PERTH, and this <hi>Fierie Doomeſday</hi> of BRITAINE, being to all your people a cauſe of Gods euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting praiſe, &amp; their preſent ioy, as the multitude made ſhewe by their <hi>Bonefires,</hi> whoſe earthly ſmokes in great meaſure aſcended the heauenly regions. It hath kindled ſuch a <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> in the furnace of my breaſt, as muſt needes bee knowne to your Maieſtie; whoſe Builder is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worker, whoſe Fewell is Affection, whoſe flames may well warme, but neuer harme you: and the more you anneere them, the more tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſhall you finde them, comforting ſuch as loue you, and conſuming ſuch as hate you: whoſe gleames I haue made firſt to glance on your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſelfe, ſecretly and vnſigned; as being vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="tcp:21759:3"/>(though they ſhould euen pleaſe you) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them; much leſſe to come in your preſence, if they ſhould offend: leauing to your Maieſties moſt royall and vpright iudgement, as you finde my Fire well built, to ſet it where you will haue it ſeene: or being fallen from his grounds, more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally to reedifie it: or if of too groſſe materialls, to purge the droſſie errors of it: or if nothing of it like you, by a breath of your Maieſties mouth vtterly to extinguiſh it. Doe as you pleaſe (Sir) for ſo long as I liue ſhall I euer loue you. Your Deliuerer be alwaies with you. From towards the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of your Maieſties <hi>Canaan, Tueſday, Doomeſday</hi> 5. <hi>Nouember.</hi> 1605.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt loyall and louing ſubiect, without any Acquiuocation.</hi> Vniuocè-catholicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:3"/>
            <head>TO BOTH SORTS, as well Vniuo-catholique, as Aequiuo-<hi>catholique Readers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man lighteth a candle to put it vnder a Buſhell;</hi> and no man buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a fire of publike ioy, and ſhutteth it vp in priuate chimnies. Thoſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue ouercome my priuate reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions: and howſoeuer the iust feare of my owne infirmities did awe mee; yet, ſeeing my betters perſwade me, my dutie bindeth me to let it goe: And ſince the royall eyes both of <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> haue once looked vpon it, what care who paſſe by it?</p>
            <p>That it was not then ſo early as others, take it not to haue beene my ſlowneſſe in beginning: for mine eares no ſooner heard, then my heart reioyced, and my hand ſet it ſelfe a worke. Neither was it my long ſomeneſſe in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it: for my whole bodie is but a cheſt of ſuch fewell. Nor yet was it my feare it ſhould quickly die; for vntill the memorie of the fact die, my Fire ſhall alwaies liue. But thus it is, whilſt vpon the point of ſuch a practiſe, all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tongs wagged, moſt pens walked, &amp; the whole world wondred, it was not then neceſſary my Fire ſhould haue appeared, being fitter to awake men now from the ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of forgetfulneſſe, then to haue accompanied the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of their ioyes.</p>
            <p>That it goeth out thus nameleſſe, doe not impute it to
<pb facs="tcp:21759:4"/>any feare of party <hi>bloodie,</hi> or <hi>firie;</hi> howſoeuer, I muſt confeſſe my ſelfe much younger in Treatiſes then yeares: for who ſhall feare to defend his Country, ſo gratious a King, ſo glorious a cauſe? No, my Fire hath no feare, and in this could I willingly ſay, <hi>Meme adſum qui feci, &amp;c.</hi> But thus it is; I finde that as the grauitie and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Authors, bring often credite to bad cauſes, and make <hi>Paradoxes</hi> paſse for probable: ſo, meane and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure inſtruments darken moſt graue &amp; true argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; then while as no man knoweth the Author, all men will take them to the matter. Wouldſt thou then haue mee leaue my Treatiſes? I beſeech thee leaue thy Treaſons: fire not our Parliament, and I ſhall not foile thy profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>To you then of the <hi>Vnivoque</hi> ſort, true Chriſtians, loyall ſubiects: let my fire ſerue to quicken your memories, comfort your hearts, confirme your hopes, and encreaſe your thankfulneſse; calling backe your mindes to thoſe Parliament mines: ſo that that day which was once thoght ſo admirable, may be held euer memorable. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get neuer then theſe two restleſſe <hi>Arch-aequiuocators,</hi> the Diuelin an Oracle, and a Ieſuite in an Oath.</p>
            <p>As for you of the vocation of <hi>Aequiuocation,</hi> halfe tongued, hollow hearted, and diſloyal Subiects (for what ſerue faire words in ſo foule warres, where no quarters are kept?) To you, I ſay, could I wiſh my fire as a flame of your dreamed Purgatory, to diuide (not your ſoules from your bodies, as you doe with vs) but that ſeede of Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your ſoules; that as you are the naturall breede of our ſoile; ſo ye might proue the loyall ſubiects of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne.</p>
            <p>Let your ſubmiſsiue <hi>Parere,</hi> meete his ſacred <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,</hi> and not dreſſe a <hi>Perire</hi> for him, his poſteritie, and
<pb facs="tcp:21759:4"/>whole ſtate, by a Popiſh, Antichriſtian, Aequiuocating Conſpiracie. But what talke I of Antichriſt? ſeeing the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites</hi> iumpe in one: the <hi>Iewes</hi> looking ſtill for Christs comming, haue loſt Chriſt come: And the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> (as all Romiſh Catholiques) looking for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts comming; hanging him on the hornes of their Altars, and harbouring him in their hearts, yet are lost by their ouer looking him.</p>
            <p>God almightie either ſeperate that Religion from you, or elſe both you and your Religion from our Region. Amen: without Acquiuocation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours as free as his Fire is,</hi> Vnivo-catholicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21759:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 47. Aetnian, reade Aetnaean.</p>
            <p>Pag. 49. penult. In, reade I.</p>
            <p>Pag. 52. 18. here it is no, reade here is no.</p>
            <p>Pag. l. 22. them, reade their.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21759:5"/>
            <head>LVCTA IACOBI: <hi>OR,</hi> Iacobs VVreſtling.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing both often and earneſtly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the eternall God, that ſome happie occaſion ſhould preſent it ſelfe, whereby I might teſtifie to the world a part of ſuch graces as he hath beſtowed on me, (<hi>Not worthy of the leaſt of all the mercies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10.</note> 
               <hi>which hee hath ſhewed vnto mee</hi>) to the glorie of his name who created mee, and for the weale of my King and Country: to both which, both by my birth and benefites hee hath bound me.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21759:6"/>
            <p>The two miraculous deliueries of our ſoueraigne Lord King IAMES, from thoſe late (wee hope laſt) and moſt of all foule, and fearefull attempts, haue occurred: which, as they are to all, a matter full of endleſſe praiſe: ſo doe they draw mee to a more deep meditation, then to be ſmothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder the buſhell of my onely breaſt. And therefore haue I (though hardily, yet) moſt humbly publiſhed the ſame vnder the title of the <hi>VVraſtling of Iacob;</hi> with which, as they haue many diſſimilitudes; and of theſe not a few fit for this purpoſe: ſo are they in many things much like, both in the preparation and action; and many good leſſons likewiſe reſulting vppon the applying of the ſequels in <hi>Iacobs</hi> victory, to that which wee iuſtly expect in this of our victorious <hi>Prince,</hi> as in the diſcourſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhall apeare.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 32. verſ. 24, 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>VVhen <hi>Iacob</hi> was left himſelfe alone, there wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him vnto the breaking of the day.</p>
               <p>And he ſaw that he could not preuaile againſt him: therefore hee touched the hollow of his thigh,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21759:6"/>and the hollow of Iacobs thigh was looſed, as he wreſtled with him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Let no man thinke it preſumption to compare theſe two <hi>Iacobs,</hi> a great <hi>Patriarch</hi> with a great <hi>Prince,</hi> a <hi>Father of the faithfull,</hi> with the <hi>defender of the faith,</hi> and a wraſtler in the ſhadowes of that heauenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> with a wraſtler for the ſubſtance of our heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before we enter then to the deſcription of theſe wraſtlings, we haue firſt to ſpeake of the perſon: then of the preparation to it.</p>
            <p>In the perſon is to bee conſidered: firſt, his name: then, his quality &amp; courſe of life.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>His name <hi>(Iacob)</hi> hath two ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; one by the firſt impoſer, his father <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac;</hi> an other from his wraſtling, impoſed by God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the firſt it ſignified a <hi>Supplanter,</hi> becauſe hee helde his brother <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heele at their birth, beeing twinnes. The other ſignification is a <hi>VVrastler,</hi> although different, yet not diſagreeing from the former: for euen from that ſame holding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21759:7"/>him by the heele, yea before it, begun their wraſtling, by the oracle of God, in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of their mother <hi>Rebecca.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.23.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>Our firſt compariſon then is from a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude: for ſo hath our ſoueraigne Lord for his name <hi>Iacob</hi> in that language. The ſignifications, though not ſo fully agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his perſon, may yet apparantly bee thus farre deriued.</p>
               <p>Firſt, although his Maieſtie be not halfe a birth, as was <hi>Iacob,</hi> but one &amp; onely ſon, cutting ſhort thereby all diſpute of titles and birth-rights with elder <hi>Eſaues;</hi> yet, as God ſaide to <hi>Rebecca, Two nations are in thy wombe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and the one ſhalbe mightier then the other, and the elder ſhall ſerue the yonger:</hi> ſo in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our princely <hi>Iacob,</hi> were two nations borne, to wit, <hi>Scotland,</hi> and his <hi>Canaan, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> whereof the elder may be ſaid to ſerue the yonger; in ſo farre as <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. being iuſtly <hi>maior</hi> or <hi>melior,</hi> is now come vnder his Maieſties gouernment, beeing then of onely <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſo <hi>meritò minor.</hi> Thus
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21759:7"/>begunne he alſo (as did <hi>Iacob</hi>) his wraſtling euen in his <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> bellie; to wit, with that olde <hi>Eſau,</hi> the roote of thoſe rauenous <hi>Ruthuens,</hi> grandfather to this <hi>Italian Edomit</hi> the late Earle of <hi>Gowrie,</hi> who preaſed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide his Highneſſe <hi>in</hi> and <hi>from</hi> his mothers wombe, as is more then manifeſt: whom God of his eternall prouidence brought forth in this world, to the inheritance of his birth-right, and preſeruation of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſo is he iuſtly called a <hi>Iacob,</hi> a <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter,</hi> or a <hi>VVraſtler,</hi> not a deceiuer, nor vſurper.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond ſignification, how farre he hath proued a <hi>VVraſtler</hi> indeede, ſhall be ſhewed in the owne roome. And thus for the name.</p>
               <p>The quality and courſe of life, hath two points, before his wraſtling, or after. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, either <hi>vnmaried,</hi> or <hi>maried: vnmaried,</hi> firſt, in getting the <hi>birth, right,</hi> then the <hi>bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>When that rough &amp; red <hi>Eſau</hi> was come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21759:8"/>out,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jen.</hi> 25.25, 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>that cunning hunter,</hi> fit for the fields, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob was a plaine man, and dwelt in tents.</hi> Here in the courſe of their liues are oppoſed, <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> to <hi>cunning, ſimplicity</hi> to <hi>fraud,</hi> and <hi>indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in tents,</hi> to a <hi>wilde barbarite.</hi> For both the diuine oracles &amp; their performances muſt teach vs, that theſe notes are good in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and bad in <hi>Eſau. Iacob</hi> was a <hi>plaine man,</hi> not that hee was doltiſh, no, for as hee was a Doue, hee was alſo a Serpent, according to the ſaying of Chriſt and ſo hee proued a <hi>plaine man,</hi> in his walking vprightly before God: a Serpent in his wiſe cariage at his encounter with <hi>Eſau.</hi> Now, cunning hunting in an other then <hi>Eſau</hi> (who poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned his birth-right to his pottage) is no opprobrie. Againe, <hi>Iacob dwelt in tents;</hi> which ſome apply to the tents of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec</hi> or <hi>Sem,</hi> that Prieſt of the moſt high God, and ſo diſcharged dutifully that law of the firſt borne, in the ſacrifices and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God, and was therefore found worthie of the birth-right, which <hi>Eſau</hi> ſet at naught, by his running aſtray in the Wilderneſſe, and ſelling it for a meſſe of pottage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21759:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>When thoſe blood-red and rough <hi>Eſaues</hi> who ſtroue with our princely <hi>Iacob,</hi> were ouercome firſt by his birth: then grew hee (and indeede greatly hath hee growen) in the <hi>plainneſse</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his indwelling in tents, as a Doue and as a Serpent: <hi>plaine</hi> in all his waies and vpright: elſe, let ſuch charge him as haue beene fruſtrate by his fraud. But lacketh hee either worldly wit, or heauenly wiſedome with <hi>Iacob?</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all ſuch as haue either conferred with his Maieſtie mouth to mouth, or yet read his manifold Treatiſes by himſelfe done: and doubtleſſe then ſhall they not aske, if hee be learned, but how hee hath learned? or rather, what hath hee not learned? ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Naturall workes, or Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall word of Cod. Surely hee dwelleth in <hi>Iacobs</hi> tents, and hath ſuffered tentations with <hi>Iacob,</hi> and beene, almoſt from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, euer a making pottage with <hi>Iacob,</hi> to pleaſure a world of wilde <hi>Eſaues.</hi> A ſecond King of <hi>Salem</hi> bringing peace to all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Hath he not beene led, as it were, in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21759:9"/>wildernes of tentations by cunning Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and cunny-catching <hi>Eſaues?</hi> who haue ſometimes perſecuted his owne perſon, ſometimes the tents of <hi>Iacob,</hi> Religion it ſelfe both publikely and vnder pretext. Haue not golden hills bene promiſed him to leaue <hi>Iacobs</hi> tents? yet did his Maieſtie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſiſt in that ſame ſtrength by which he now lately preuailed: and ſaid not with <hi>Caeſar</hi> and others, <hi>Si</hi> (ſi) <hi>iuſiurandum violan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, regnandi cauſa violandum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here mee thinkes I doe euen heare ſome obiecting againſt certaine breaches, ſlippes and errors, eſcaped in the courſe of our <hi>Iacobs</hi> gouernment. True, elſe hee were not a <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2.</note> but a <hi>Iah,</hi> that is, a God. And were there not euen in that Patriarches houſe ſtrange errors, when hee bad them remoue their ſtrange gods? But ſuch were then our <hi>ſottiſh, ſcottiſh</hi> humours; and ſuch are now our <hi>brutiſh, brittiſh</hi> humours, to be euer looſe tongued, rather <hi>imputing,</hi> or <hi>imping</hi> (as it were) faultes in our Prince, wherof he is free; then either ſupplying his infirmities, or praiſing his vertues: as if all were then repaired, when the Prince is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21759:9"/>but of this afterwards. This one thing auouch I onely here, that our <hi>Iacob</hi> hath (I will not ſay of all men, fearing flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie) but of all Princes, Monarches, both moſt and beſt mixed knowledge in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt &amp; worthieſt matters. One word then, God encreaſe and ſanctifie.</p>
               <p>This for the <hi>Birth-right:</hi> followeth the <hi>Bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> thus enioying worthily the <hi>Birth-right,</hi> muſt needes haue alſo the <hi>Bleſsing</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing therevnto, which his mother <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> bringeth alſo to paſſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.5.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>Our <hi>Iacob,</hi> (hauing ſince his birth, for both his parents, but his onely mother as <hi>parens partus aut ſanguinis,</hi> and her late Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>parens poſſeſsionis ſeu haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> and ſo iuſtly his mother) hath (I ſay) in ſpite of all repining <hi>Eſaues,</hi> borne away the bleſſing proper to his birth-right, in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21759:10"/>both his mothers. For as to his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall mother, howſoeuer ſuch <hi>Eſaues</hi> as ſtroue with him in her belly, went about by all meanes to fruſtrate him of her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, by throwing her from her throne, and inueſting him in the kingdome before he was ripe, putting the ſcepter in his hand before he was able to beare it, &amp; the ſword before he could ſway it; yet, he growing in yeares, and more in grace, his obedient behauiour, together with his innocencie, ſo ſweetely ſmelled in her noſe (<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.27, 28.</note> as did <hi>Iacob</hi> to his father) that ſhee proued both a louing <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> and a bleſſing <hi>Iſaac</hi> to her Princely <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to his other <hi>Rebeccah Haereditatis,</hi> whom our <hi>Iacob</hi> in end onely had for all, and did vſe as all; the world did ſee, how little all ſuch <hi>Eſaus</hi> as ſtroue in title with our <hi>Iacob,</hi> did preuaile at her hand; yea, and kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by her hand; and the full bleſſing reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to her owne <hi>Iacob;</hi> howſoeuer ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lented the publication of it, partly looking to her ſelfe, whom ſhe muſt firſt loue; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like a louing mother, ſometimes frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on that childe ſhee beſt loueth. But as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21759:10"/>her Maieſtie waxed olde, and became full of daies, and dimme eyed with<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſhee then called for her <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſo fully bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him.</p>
               <p>Thus farre, both of the <hi>Birth-right</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> Followeth the <hi>Mariage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>Next is <hi>Iacob</hi> ſet on his <hi>Mariage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.1.</note> and ſent to his owne kindred, forbidden by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to match with the <hi>Cananites.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is ſhortly meant, not onely the carnall alliance, but alſo and more, the ſpirituall coniunction to be reſpected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> being now without father or mother naturall, is by that all-ſufficient God of <hi>Iacob</hi> inſtructed, conducted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from matching with the kindred of <hi>Cham,</hi> promiſing him golden hills, &amp; <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> before the fulneſſe of time, if ſo be he would leaue the tents of <hi>Iacob, Religion:</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21759:11"/>ſo is hee mooued to goe: euen to his owne kindred, with whom his predeceſſors had happily matched before, and neerer to the tents of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point of the <hi>Mariage</hi> hath alſo two parts. Firſt, <hi>Iacobs</hi> Iourney. Secondly, his ſucceſſe in his Mariage. The Iourney a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine two things. Firſt, the courſe of his paſſage. Secondly, his viſion in his paſſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacobs</hi> paſsing was towards the Eaſt, his trauailes long and weariſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> held alſo Eaſtward, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the ordinarie cuſtome of Princes) paſt in his owne perſon <hi>per mare, per terras, per tot diſcrimina rerum.</hi> Followeth the <hi>Viſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw a Ladder reaching to heauen;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12.</note> Chriſt with Angells on the Ladder <hi>going vp
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21759:11"/>and downe:</hi> God aboue it, promiſing two things. Firſt, to bee his God, and bring him backe againe. Secondly, to giue him that ſame Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> that hee promiſed to his Fathers, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> well inſtructed in that Viſion of the Ladder, Chriſt our Sauiour; hee found the fruites and performance of the firſt part of the promiſe of thoſe miniſtring Angells, who walked (as it were) vpon the verie <hi>Ship-ladders</hi> for his ſafetie, againſt theſe droues of diuelliſh <hi>VVitches,</hi> as hee twice croſſed the ſeas: here was hee our <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> God; thus broght he him ſafely home.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond part. The correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence may bee thus applied (without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) ſpeaking of <hi>Canaan,</hi> not as it was a type of the Kingdome of heauen. <hi>Canaan</hi> was thriſe to three ſeuerall perſons promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> &amp; now here to <hi>Iacob:</hi> So is our <hi>Iacob</hi> (now enioying his <hi>Canaan</hi>) euen the thirde perſon from his grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who firſt iſſued out of the loynes of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21759:12"/>King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, whoſe line expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the perſon of that renowned Ladie, the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who contented to liue continent, and ſo wedded to Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in her choiſe of <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi> full 43. yeres in peace and piety gouerned her people; a mirror to her ſex, a miracle to her age, and a patterne to all princely poſterity: who as at her departing, ſhe did part her people with a great bleſſing; ſo did ſhe impart to them a greater, in the perſon of her and our <hi>Iacob;</hi> a <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 5.4.</note> ſetting all his ſubiects at reſt on all ſides from all their enemies, of whom ſhe might iuſtly ſay, <hi>Si non peperi, ſalte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reperi quem peperiſſe volui:</hi> delighting euer ſince his entry (moſt <hi>Salomon</hi>-like) in the works of <hi>Vnitie,</hi> by knitting in one the heartes of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, already ſeated in one Continent, a cauſe to make vs coaleſce in one: and both by ſea diuided from Princes adiacent; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming hereby, that no forrainer ſhould beare rule in this Iland: whereof that Law, <hi>Nemo tranſmarinus, &amp;c.</hi> was a prophecie: both of one language, telling vs that we are not to build vp a <hi>Babylon</hi> by diuiſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.6.7.</note> but reedifie a <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> through power of that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21759:12"/>
                  <hi>Vnitie,</hi> which hath for the moſt infallible bond of our <hi>Vnion,</hi> ioined vs already in one <hi>Religion:</hi> onely impeded by the common enemie, both of his title, and life, <hi>Dolmans, Perſons,</hi> traitour Catholiques, deuouring all vnder colour of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if theſe <hi>Doomeſeday Prieſts</hi> had euer ſaid <hi>Meſſe</hi> vpon this Altar, of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſed be hee that remoueth his neighbours march:</hi> then had they no more transferred the right of a Crowne for Religion, then Religion for a Crowne. No,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.53.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> when they parted at <hi>Mizpa,</hi> were of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Religions, and ſwore by diuers gods, that they ſhuld not come ouer that march for others euill. Or if the Popes in this point were as good nowe, as was <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> that <hi>Romane</hi> King, who placed that ſtone <hi>Abaddir,</hi> as the God of Marches in their Capitole, puniſhing the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors by death; then (I ſay) the Popes prieſts had preached with <hi>Pompilius</hi> the god of <hi>Marches,</hi> more then the God of <hi>Meſſes:</hi> the firſt beeing plainer in the Scripture then the other, and not to ſtirre vppe ſuch <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaues.</hi> to quarrell <hi>Iacob</hi> in his Birth-right.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21759:13"/>But let that Ethnicke teach thoſe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. Onely hath this corner of my <hi>Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> delited to ſport it ſelfe, with theſe two delightfull Princes, <hi>Rebecca</hi> and her <hi>Iacob.</hi> Followeth the ſucceſſe of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
               <p>The cheefeſt bleſsing heere recounted, is, the beautifull children that God gaue to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
               <p>So hath our <hi>Iacob</hi> more <hi>Oliue plants about his table,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128 4.</note> then moſt part of chriſtian Princes. And thus farre for the Compariſon of our two <hi>Iacobs,</hi> in name and life a <hi>Simili.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Their Diſsimilitudes.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>The Patriarch <hi>Iacob</hi> had but one <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our princely <hi>Iacob</hi> had many <hi>Eſaues;</hi> a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of <hi>Eſaues,</hi> a Doomeſday of <hi>Eſaues.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21759:13"/>
               <head>The Preperation to the VVrastling.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>Now <hi>Iacob</hi> taketh his Iourney at Gods command to make for his own Country,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.3.27, 42, 43.</note> where <hi>Eſau</hi> was before him, whoſe terrors began againe to touch him: which he had hitherto eſcaped by his mothers meanes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Iacob,</hi> being about ſome fourteene yeres of age, taketh the fields &amp; the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his owne hands; &amp; ſo is by the ſon of that old <hi>Eſau,</hi> who wraſtled with him in his mothers wombe, the ſecond time aſſailed.<note place="margin">Ruthuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode.</note> Thus are the mother &amp; the ſon, Princes; by the father &amp; the ſon, traitours; twice perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: for the which this ſecond <hi>Eſau</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards loſt his head.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Diſsimilitudes of of thoſe <hi>Iacobs</hi> in their Preparation.</head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriarch feared his brother <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> becauſe hee had preuented him, both
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21759:14"/>in his <hi>Birth-right</hi> and <hi>Bleſsing:</hi> and ſo the leſſe danger being foreſeene.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> our Prince, had no feare, becauſe no fault: and ſo the leſſe feare, the more daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: for <hi>Eſau Gowrie</hi> had his Birth-right pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to him of our <hi>Iacob,</hi> which olde <hi>Eſau</hi> his father had iuſtly forfeited. And thoſe Catholique fire-brands held moſt of their honours of our <hi>Iacob:</hi> Many oddes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> goeth to his brothers roomes, to poſſeſſe himſelfe in <hi>Eſaues Birth-right,</hi> and thence is his feare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 2.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> is bidden by <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſo loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to be welcome: ſo, that <hi>Iacob</hi> doubted; our <hi>Iacob</hi> truſted <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 3.</head>
                  <p>Againe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> ſent gifts to aſſwage <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21759:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 3.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> is propined by <hi>Eſau,</hi> promiſed great wealth, heapes of gold.</p>
                  <p>And thus for the preparation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Followeth the Compariſon of the Eſaues. Firſt, a Simili.</head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſau</hi> was red.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 1.</head>
                  <p>So are our <hi>Iacobs Eſaues,</hi> blood-red, and fire-red.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſau</hi> was a cunning Hunter, and dwelt in the fields.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſau Gowrie</hi> was (as wee call it) a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Realm-raker,</hi> a hunter, able to catch the Diuell. And our <hi>Roman Eſaus,</hi> cunning <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15.</note> 
                     <hi>compaſsing Sea and land, to make one of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, and ſo make them ſeuen-fold more the ſonne of Sathan</hi> then before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21759:15"/>
               <head>Similitudes of our <hi>Iacobs, Eſaus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themſelues.</head>
               <p>They haue firſt one generall cauſe. Thou killedſt olde <hi>Eſau</hi> my father (ſaid bloody <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> to <hi>Iacob</hi>) and <hi>Romane Eſau,</hi> thou killeſt our father the <hi>Pope.</hi> an honourable quarrel for <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwers for <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Eſau Gowrie</hi> thy father, was a Traitour to the King; and ſo the law killed him. But as I was then <hi>Minor:</hi> ſo by my owne cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie haue I put thee in better caſe then I found thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Roman Eſaues,</hi> your father was, and is ſtill, a Traitour both to God and Kings, whom God by his breath hath and ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh: which as it began ere I was borne, ſo haue I neuer yet put you in worſe caſe then I found you.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they had all one end, deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prince and people, ſword and fire, body and ſoule.</p>
               <p>Follow the Diſſimilitudes of the <hi>Eſaus</hi> of thoſe two <hi>Iacobs.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21759:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>That <hi>Eſau</hi> was elder Brother of that <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and ſo by lawe of nature might chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a preheminence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Iacobs Eſaues</hi> were all younger, no brothers, but ſubiects bound to <hi>Iacobs</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>That <hi>Eſau</hi> denounced a faire warre, by open conuocation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Eſaues</hi> pronounced a falſe peace, by lurking <hi>Aequiuocation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>Eſau <hi>and</hi> Iacob <hi>met and were agreed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.1.</note> and ſo <hi>peace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Eſaus</hi> alſo met our <hi>Iacob,</hi> and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, and ſo perfide. For firſt, <hi>Eſau Gowrie</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21759:16"/>(as my ſelfe was both eare and eie witnes) at his firſt reencounter with our <hi>Iacob</hi> at <hi>Falkland,</hi> was thus by his Highneſſe entrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted; That as he had ſeen more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others his fellowes, and (as his Maieſtie had heard) made good fruites of his trauailes: ſo hee would pray him to giue proofes and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of it in the partes of his preferment, for reformation of ſuch enormities as his Maieſty was then about. All was accepted &amp; promiſed. But he was hollow-hearted, as he quickly proued: for he aequiuocated.</p>
                  <p>Againe, <hi>Romane Eſaus</hi> met (among others) our <hi>Iacob,</hi> both at his entry to <hi>England,</hi> and at the <hi>Parliament:</hi> yea ſome of them receiued to inward ſeruices. In this they all agree, that from, and in the ſame place they agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Iacob,</hi> the one inuited, the other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted him to his death. A bloody ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet! Afirie Religion! The firſt ſacked bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the ſecond ſacrificed ſoules:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 7.5.</note> not a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> ſacrifice to dedicate houſes, but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice both <hi>Salomon</hi> &amp; his houſes: not with fire from aboue, but from the bowells of the earth below: nothing of God, but all of the Diuell their deuiſer: a fine <hi>holocauſt, a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21759:16"/>ſacrifice, a faith!</hi> as Catholique, as the whore that hatched it, euer either purging by the force of her powder, or<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.2.</note> poiſoning with the cuppe of her fornication, all the Princes of the earth.</p>
                  <p>Thus for the Compariſon of <hi>Eſaus.</hi> Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth now the Wraſtling it ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>And when <hi>Iacob</hi> was left alone, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24.</note>
               </head>
               <p>When Man is weakeſt and moſt ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then are all ſorts of aſſaults moſt forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Iacob</hi> was now alone, not ſo much as the day-light to beare him witneſſe. But as to the ſimilitudes of theſe wraſtlings, are not that <hi>Iacobs</hi> recorded in <hi>Geneſis?</hi> And our <hi>Iacobs,</hi> yet ſcarce paſt our eyes, much leſſe our memories; and are alſo fully recorded according to the truth to the poſteritie: ſo that I (who will neither adde nor paire) can nothing mend them. Onely I doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue here, how the almighty God did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our <hi>Iacob</hi> with weapons fitting each conflict: againſt bloody <hi>Eſau,</hi> with <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Eloquence. Force,</hi> in claſping (as he did) with him. <hi>Eloquence,</hi> as with ſtratagems to compaſſe him.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21759:17"/>
               <p>Eloquence, a rare vertue, and rareſt in this Prince, in whoſe tong, ſo many good lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages dwell, as in their naturall ſoile.</p>
               <p>Againſt fierie <hi>Eſau,</hi> with more ſubtile weapons, <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Prouidence: Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in conſtruing that Letter to <hi>Monteagle: Prouidence,</hi> in ripping vp the danger. O here did <hi>mount</hi> an <hi>Eagle</hi> in the heauenly skie of our <hi>Iacobs</hi> iudgement, elſe both Prince and people had flowen as fierie Eagles in the ayre. Here became our <hi>Iacob,</hi> from a milde <hi>Doue,</hi> a wiſe <hi>Serpent:</hi> elſe both Prince and people had beene ſtung with firie Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And here our noble hunting <hi>Iacob,</hi> out-hunted thoſe <hi>Romiſh Eſaues,</hi> elſe both Prince and people had taſted a pipe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique <hi>Tobacco.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The differences of the VVraſtlings.</head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 1.</head>
                  <p>God wraſtled with <hi>Iacob,</hi> in ſhape of a man.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 1.</head>
                  <p>Men poſſeſſed, or Sathan in ſhape of men wraſtled with our <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21759:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 2.</head>
                  <p>God wraſtled with <hi>Iacob</hi> for aſſurance of his ſafetie from his brother <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 2.</head>
                  <p>Our <hi>Iacob</hi> wraſtled with his deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, fighteth before he feareth, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth before hee be knowne in the field.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 3.</head>
                  <p>God wraſtled with <hi>Iacob</hi> for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 3.</head>
                  <p>Our Doomeſday prieſts blow vp our <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> becauſe he will not renounce his faith: a meruailous Religion, all ſtanding by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, dead mens bones, reliques for exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes; new found<note n="*" place="margin">Virgo Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis, &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers collis. Lypſius.</note> Ladies for all olde diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. And now, hell it ſelfe, a fire for kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Catholique Religion. <hi>En hic, illic, &amp; eſthic eſt Chriſtus Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21759:18"/>
               <head>And he ſaw that he could not preuaile against him; therefore he touched the hollow of his thigh.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.25.</note>
               </head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>God wraſtling with <hi>Iacob,</hi> could not, that is, would not preuaile; for ſo was his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; yet hee touched the hollow of his thigh, to witneſſe vnto him that hee was a mighty Wraſtler, and for a remembrance to ſeeke for his help in the day of affliction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>Our wraſtlers could not, becauſe God would not ſuffer them preuail; yet had they power to touch the hollow of our <hi>Iacobs</hi> thigh, by reaſon ſo much blood was ſhed for his ſafetie, which is iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended vnder the perſon of <hi>Iacob;</hi> yea, one indeede thruſt through the very thigh: teaching ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our <hi>Iacob,</hi> that this conflict ſhould not paſſe (as no more did it) without a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall for his amendement. And ſo, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he eſcaped in his owne perſon,<note place="margin">Vicounts Fenton, and Hadaington.</note> yet loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on thoſe whoſe blood bled as in his owne body: of which, two yet aliue and linked to <hi>Iacob,</hi> as out of diuine prouidence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21759:18"/>for two witneſſes of Gods mercy, &amp; two wakeners of their Maiſters memorie for a perpetuall thankfulneſſe of this deliuerie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>And the man <hi>(or God in the forme of man)</hi> ſaid, Let me goe, for the day appeareth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.26.</note> but hee ſaid, I wil not let thee goe, except thou bleſſe me.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition. 1.</head>
                  <p>The day thus appearing, and <hi>Iacob</hi> being victorious, the Angel then would haue bin gone. But <hi>Iacob</hi> fearing more and great wraſtlings, would firſt haue a further bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application. 1.</head>
                  <p>Thus alſo did appeare the daie to our <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> as well from our <hi>Diluge,</hi> as our <hi>Doomeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Papists,</hi> who wraſtled indeede moſt in the night. And God grant a fullie clear day for clearing the cloudes of this laſt wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: for which my <hi>Bone-fire</hi> kindleth two lightes from two corners. The one, to let vs throughly ſee and examine the cauſes giuen out by theſe <hi>Eſaus</hi> againſt our <hi>Iacob.</hi> The other, for a deuouring death to al ſuch as haue wrongfully wraſtled.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21759:19"/>
                  <p>The cauſes (as the <hi>Eſaus</hi>) were two fold; <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Fire; Blood</hi> in the <hi>Parthian Eſau</hi> of <hi>Perth,</hi> falſly charged (as ſaide is) and truly remoued both by law and minoritie. But now turne it ouer, <hi>Iacob</hi> is <hi>Maior</hi> and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; then purge the land from blood, elſe what excuſe againſt the next bloodie wraſtling: for though <hi>Gowrie</hi> falſly allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged blood, yet did God at that time iuſtly wraſtle with <hi>Iacob</hi> for blood:<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> yea, blood had then moſt like a flood of <hi>Noah</hi> drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the land: ſo that whilſt your Highneſſe was on the toppe of all <hi>Gowries</hi> houſe, yet were you in blood to your gorge. But ſince it pleaſed our good God to make eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> owne houſe your <hi>Arke</hi> of <hi>Noah</hi> in the midſt of that diluge, and alſo to ſettle ſince, the great Arke of your royall eſtate ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly vpon theſe ſweet <hi>Mount</hi> of <hi>Armenia</hi> it followeth then (Sir) that like a faithful <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> you ſend out ſtill ſome to ſpie, how the diluge of blood decreaſeth in your land, not <hi>Corbie-meſſengers</hi> (for wee haue too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch in truſt already) but <hi>Doues,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Or Rauen-meſſengers. Gen. <hi>8.7, 8, 9</hi>
                     </note> more neere to <hi>Noahs</hi> owne nature.</p>
                  <p>Now (Sir) theſe be my moſt temperate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21759:19"/>flames I ſpoke of at the beginning. A baſe affection will (euen in your preſence) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime your praiſe, &amp; perhaps, a part againe diſclaim his colors, &amp; aequiuocate; ſo haue I here made you a <hi>Iacob:</hi> but it muſt be a migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty loue dare ſpeake once of a Prince his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes; and this dare I, knowing I deale not with a proud <hi>Pope, non poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> errare;</hi> but with a moſt chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> king, knowing <hi>Quis ſit qui non erret.</hi> And therefore, leſt I be met with the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> reply, who being asked, which of all beaſts he held for moſt cruell, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thus, <hi>Exferis, Tyrannis, exmitibus adulator,</hi> will I (I ſay) be about to be as free (if it bee poſſible) from flattery, as they haue found your Maieſty fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyranny; telling them (and moſt truely) that as thoſe bloody eſcapes were not the faultes of your perſon, but of your Time, not of Nature, but neceſſity, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtoms tyranny, not your authority, born before you, &amp; buried by you: So hath your Highneſſe already wel begun to giue vs (as with <hi>Noah</hi>) a new generation, both by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording our barbarous feedes, or enmities, and crying downe our cut-throte piſtolls; wherein your Maieſtie had euen a newe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21759:20"/>wraſtling and ſmall aſſiſtance. Onelie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth then, that as you are a <hi>Iacob</hi> and a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hunter (not forgetting your calling with <hi>Eſau</hi>) you out hunt ſtill all ſuch bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Hunters as brought you to thoſe bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die bathes you then eſcaped. So noble hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſince your Horne is alreadie blowen, the Forreſt your own, the Foxes a foote, your louing ſubiects your Hounds, God the Maiſter Huntſman; goe on in this happie Huntſ-vp, whoſe hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are ſo well heard by that <hi>holy one of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> And thus for the cauſes of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge.</p>
                  <p>The cauſes of our <hi>Doomeſ-day</hi> are more ſubtile &amp; quinteſſented. Religion groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on traditions, the chiefe foundament of all Treaſons, whoſe principles are <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> whoſe ground is from the decay of Kings and Countries, and whoſe end ſhall bee <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> Here (as <hi>Eſau Gowrie</hi> falſlie vrged blood) doe <hi>Romane Eſaues</hi> falſlie vrge firie perſecution, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of our <hi>Iacob</hi> is moſt, (if not too much) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and free: yet God iuſtlie wraſtleth heere with <hi>Iacob</hi> for fire, that is, a firie tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21759:20"/>too long neglected for purging this Land, from ſuch firie breathed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, increaſed by his Maieſties too much clemencic.</p>
                  <p>This error (Sir) as the former, we know to be no waies of your nature, howſoeuer of negligence: for as Princes are ſaide to haue manie and long eares, yet heare they (for the moſt part) but what their ſubiects bring to them. And wee know this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique cauſe hath beene often diſputed (and perhappes to your owne face) vnder <hi>eſt, &amp; non eſt;</hi> both touching their growth, and your danger: and the Negatiue rather preuailing, becauſe Runnagates were cropen in credite that coulde aequiuocate; till now your Maieſtie hath had ſo liuelie a demonſtration of it: ſo doe I here (as a man of his maiſters owne Religion) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch that <hi>Ita eſt;</hi> yea, much better haue we ſeene it goe ſince we knew your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie neuer better minded then now. Then (Sir) <hi>eſt,</hi> you haue eſcaped it, <hi>erit,</hi> beware with it, vnleſſe in time you ſee too it. Alas, that ſacred eares ſhould bee concredited to Syrene tongues.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21759:21"/>
                  <p>The other corner of my Fire, was for a light to ſearch out and puniſh this late Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Treaſon. Away then (Sir) with too much of your olde clemencie: Clemencie, the moſt dangerous companion that euer your Maieſty caried about with you, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a part deſiderated in many Princes. For of all the rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s your Highneſſe hath bene exerciſed with from your cradle, this of Doomeſday is the onelie perfection.</p>
                  <p>Some ſeemed in your life (though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully) to redreſſe their own particulars. The diluge, by your death, a general deſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but this <hi>Doomeſday</hi> (as ſaid <hi>Winter</hi>) ſtrook at the roote,<note place="margin">In hù Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Baſilicon Doron.</note> &amp; ſo fell all the branches. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (Sir) howſoeuer you refer the * puniſhment of treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prince, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling therby in ſome caſes to mitigate the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of ſome merciles Monarches, yet in this point, pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs your people, who muſt bee a chiefe party, euen to tell your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, that none guilty can eſcape correction.</p>
                  <p>As a husband (Sir) you are but a priuate man; and as a father, but priuate; then if your owne halfe, or owne bowells, could haue thus offended, Correction onely as a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21759:21"/>Prince are you a publike perſon, &amp; in that caſe, are we <hi>alterum Relatum:</hi> whoſe nature is, (as your Maieſtie well knoweth) that the one being taken out of the way, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite periſheth: wee haue beene cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled thus with your Maieſtie neere ſome fortie yeares, and if our head now ſhould be ſo vntimely cut off, our old bodie, with a young head, (howſoeuer of higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation) might bee feared to produce monſtrous effects.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Then he ſaide <hi>(to Iacob)</hi> what is thy name?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26, 27, 28.</note> who anſwered, <hi>Iacob.</hi> And hee ſaid, thou ſhalt bee called <hi>Iacob</hi> no more, but <hi>Iſrael:</hi> for ſince thou haſt had power with God, thou ſhalt alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile amongſt men.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>Here <hi>Iacob</hi> receiueth of God to the former benefite, that future bleſſing whereof that was a type, ſealed vp now with a moſt forcible ſacrament in changing of his name; and was fully performed in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities enioying of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21759:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>We haue here alſo on both ſides (<hi>Iacobs,</hi> and his <hi>Eſaus</hi>) certaine ſacraments, ſignes and prodigies. One difference is, that our <hi>Iacob</hi> now enioyeth his <hi>Canaan,</hi> which that Patriarch had here, but in expectation: wherein our <hi>Iacob</hi> hath had alſo a change in ſome ſort of his name from <hi>Sixt</hi> to <hi>Firſt,</hi> from <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> to Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> thereby vniting, as it were, ſo many Tribes vnder one title of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our ſignes were, thoſe ſtrange and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie workings of the firmament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, preceeding the blaſt.</p>
                  <p>Our prodigies were, theſe ſtrange gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Lions in the Tower, whilſt the Traitours build in the Towne. Some thought <hi>mala omina,</hi> becauſe wee were too neere <hi>mala omnia;</hi> but I conſtrue it rather as a mercie of God, who, as hee had giuen his Maieſtie by true diſcent from one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixe grand-fathers, a Lion to his Armes, and planted in his heart that true <hi>Lion of the Tribe of Iudah:</hi> ſo would hee ſeale
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21759:22"/>vppe vnto him, how ſtrongly hee would ſtand for him in this wraſtling, by making rather a Creation then Generation of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to carrie, as it were, his Maieſties own word <hi>In defence</hi> againſt all ſuch as <hi>ſhall fight againſt the Lambe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ren.</hi> 17.14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the part of our <hi>Eſaues,</hi> were alſo chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged names, for changing of Kings and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as was in <hi>Faulkes,</hi> that Cotholique <hi>Falcon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then they tooke (their) bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Winters confeſſion.</note> onely fit for ſealing vp ſo bloodie a ſacrifice. Now <hi>qualis pater, talis proles,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Packe,</hi> their <hi>Primar</hi> their <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> their <hi>Sacrament,</hi> their <hi>Seale;</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> their head; Good Lord who was <hi>Priest?</hi> Of Conſcience I might bee perſwaded it was the <hi>Diuell</hi> in his <hi>Pontificalibus;</hi> all good <hi>Aequiuocators.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But alas, for a little of our <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine wiſdome here, to examine this ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall operation of this their Sacrament, as whether there was in it a perfite Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation or not. And if a perfite Tranſubſtantiation, <hi>tantus, quantus, totus, quotus, talis, qualis, &amp; caetera, reliqua, omnia, nihil,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21759:23"/>conforme to their fictions, then what did it ſeale vppe in theſe receiuers? <hi>Saluation</hi> or <hi>Damnation?</hi> If Saluation, then farewell hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for my part: for ſuch a villanie was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of ſince firſt the <hi>execrated Pope</hi> was <hi>ex-ſcreated.</hi> Damnation? who dare iudge, leſt he be iudged? for it may be (and God grant) they die penitent, and ſo be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. I haue knowne the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment worke in men, both a ſorrow and abſtinence from ſmaller ſinnes: but to ſwallow their God, for ſealing vppe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in ſo many harts, to ſacrifice their owne ſoueraigne Lord, with ſo manie ſoules; nine <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> that is plaine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>True Religion is like true coine; it hath alwaies on the one ſide God, in ſome word, and the King on the other: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not ſo, is counterfeited. This miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble age is too much exerciſed, vnder pretext of Religion, <hi>aut in delendis aut declinandis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>God ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10.20</note> 
                     <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought:</hi> Poperie ſaith, Curſe him not in thy thought, but ere euer hee be able to know
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21759:23"/>thy thought, giue him a blaſt, aequiuocate: &amp; then if the blaſt hold not, hang him that miſſed him, but if it holde, canonize him that hit him. Hang all <hi>Aequiuocators.</hi> But lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to eternize my Fire from the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but rather the quality of my fewell, I go about to that corner of our great expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Maieſtie, after the example of <hi>Iacob,</hi> in a thankfull memorie of ſo great and gratious a deliuery.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>And <hi>Iacob,</hi> called the name of the place Peniel:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30.</note> for <hi>(ſaid he) I</hi> haue ſeene God.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>One thing doth <hi>Iacob</hi> here immediately after his deliuery, and an other afterward. chap. 35. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Apodoſis,</hi> or Application.</head>
                  <p>So did our <hi>Iacob,</hi> immediately after his deliuerie, goe to <hi>Bethel;</hi> that is, Gods houſe; and there ſolemnly praiſed <hi>the mighty one of Iſrael,</hi> as the onely author of his deliuerie, to which all his people ſaid <hi>Amen.</hi> And this <hi>Tueſday</hi> beeing as it were <hi>Tuyce-day</hi> for his wraſtling: firſt, <hi>dies Martis</hi> by blood: and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21759:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21759:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21759:25"/>now <hi>Vulcan</hi> by fire: ſo hath his Maieſtie turned the ſame daies for euer in daies of Gods diuine ſeruice, <hi>in perpetuam &amp; religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am reimemoriam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Then <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaide vnto his houſhold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2.</note> and vnto all that were with him: Put away the ſtrange gods that are among you.</head>
               <p>Now (Sir) haue we done with words of praiſe, and come to workes of praiſe. Wee ſee euen in our Patriarchs houſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers a deformitie, <hi>ſtrange gods.</hi> The like ſeeth your Maieſtie both in your Court &amp; Country. We ſee alſo in <hi>Iacob</hi> a conſtant &amp; couragious zeale to reforme both, without exception of perſons; yea, he ſuffered not ſo much as his own <hi>Rahel</hi> to keepe the ſtollen gods of her father <hi>Laban:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.19.</note> what leſſe can we look for of your Maieſty? No, what leſſe do your beginnings already promiſe vnto vs?<note n="*" place="margin">Baſilicon Doron.</note> Then (Sir) conform to your own grounds; <hi>begin your reformation euen at your elbow, and ſo to the extremities of your kingdome.</hi> So this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my <hi>Bonefire</hi> for your houſe, the next for your people. For both one generall.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21759:25"/>
               <p>
                  <q>No truſting a Princes perſon to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; nor the keyes of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth to Gouernours, diuided from their Maiſter in religion: chiefly profeſſing that religion, which onely of all, maintaineth for a <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> to cut off <hi>Maximos,</hi> for a <hi>Principle</hi> to kill <hi>Principes:</hi> a practiſe without any preſident, whervpon hath enſued this <hi>late, little treaſon.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ironia.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="antitheses">
               <head>Antitheſes for the people.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> came not to his <hi>Canaan</hi> by confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: neither ſhall your Maieſtie euer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy long your <hi>Canaan</hi> by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacobs</hi> poſterity had a great many mightie Nations to caſt out of his <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 5.1.</note> differing from the true ſeruice of God: &amp; your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie hath but one, who will neither ſerue God nor you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> his poſteritie made (but raſhly) a couenant with the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> in <hi>Canaan:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 9, 3.</note> your Maieſties couenant was craued by Romiſh catholikes, refuſed by you; further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery particular mans behauior &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience might demerite, whereof my ſelfe was a witneſſe; too much grace for ſo much ingratitude.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21759:26"/>
               <p>The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were contented to draw water &amp; hew wood for the houſe of <hi>Iacobs</hi> God. The Romiſh Catholiques wil kindle fire and burne wood to blow you vp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye do not ſuffer them ſerue their own god. Then (Sir) away with them: and as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your <hi>Diluge,</hi> you purged your Land of bloud: ſo after this <hi>Doomeſday,</hi> purge vs from <hi>ſtrange gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At that <hi>Diluge</hi> your Highneſſe made a law,<note place="margin">In the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament next following.</note> that no man ſhould beare the name (much leſſe the nature) of <hi>Eſau Gowrie:</hi> let alſo your lawes nowe aboliſh both the name and nature of <hi>Romiſh Eſaues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truſt not their Oathes for <hi>Non eſt fides</hi> ſake; nor their ſubſcription, for they admit interpretation by way of <hi>Aequiuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> they breed <hi>Diſtinguoes,</hi> which draw on your <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguoes.</hi> The onely <hi>vniuoque</hi> way is, Away with them.</p>
               <p>But this were hote. No wonder ſeeing it is the breath of a fire: can my fire, in a fierie ſubiect, againſt falſe firy ſubiects, ſpeake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a fiery language? My Fire burneth only for King &amp; Country, and yet quicke with both: ſhall it be cold with thoſe that would burne both?</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21759:26"/>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But <hi>All</hi> would not ſo, therefore all muſt not away. <hi>Reſp.</hi> God knoweth how many do, or how long they ſhall think ſo. Yet all Popery away, ſeeing al ſorts of Papiſts haue thought ſo. Marke my Induction.</p>
               <p>Eccleſiaſtiques and Laicks haue thought ſo: of Eccleſ. Jeſuits &amp; Secular Prieſts haue thought ſo. Of Ieſuits, Prieſts, and Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials haue thought ſo. Of Laicks, Subiects againſt any Prince, and euen againſt their owne Prince haue thought ſo: Subiectes Seruants, againſt both their owne Prince and Maiſter haue thought ſo. Of late, all theſe Diſciples, and Children thought ſo: and of olde, <hi>Papa pater,</hi> and <hi>Roma mater,</hi> both thought and taught ſo. And J pray, if this Pope-religious blaſt had not beene, what Ieſuits, Prieſts, Subiects, or Seruants of that ſort could giue more eſpera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then theſe ſame that were in? None, then ſtill away withall Popery. And ſince Rebel-religion is al the riches we haue from <hi>Rome,</hi> his Ma: may better ſay to father <hi>Pope,</hi> then the King of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 14, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Sodome</hi> to father <hi>Abraham, Da mihi animas, bona cape tibi.</hi> Let the Pope
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21759:27"/>take home both his <hi>goods</hi> and his <hi>Gods,</hi> let the ſoules bee our Soueraignes: Soules in <hi>Ciuilibus</hi> properly and peculiarly; in <hi>Sacris,</hi> to follow their <hi>Moſes,</hi> leading them from <hi>Pharoas</hi> ſlauery to Gods ſeruice, and if this cannot be, let <hi>Gods, goods,</hi> and <hi>good men,</hi> all goe.</p>
               <p>Then, though we truſt none, there is no fiery triall; blowing ouer Sea, is not blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the World. Truſt them: No. J haue ſeene (not ſo long ſince) Papo-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, ſubſcribe once, ſweare and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe twice; Communicate, ſweare, and ſubſcribe thrice; &amp; fall back foure times: yea ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come to that height, as to bear ſome office in our Church, and yet remaine Romiſh. Good Lord: But ſeeing I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale my owne name, I will not reueale theirs, howſoeuer ready to giue proofe of all, to ſuch as both know me, and haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to call me to my aunſwere, in truth without Acquinocation for all are yet aliue. So, <hi>Non eſt fides ſera anda hereticis,</hi> that Is to ſay, <hi>Nulla eſt fides his Catholicis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here the pitty of bewitching Popery,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21759:27"/>that Gentlemen, who in their ciuill ſociety, make conſcience to breake their ſmaleſt promiſes; yet by a poſition of Romiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are ſo farre cooſened, as to conceyte, not onely a lawfulneſſe, but euen a merit, to breake all the bondes of <hi>Nature, God,</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> Blow vp all. Then, ſhall the ſafety of King and State depend vpon their diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their Religion? Or rather diſpoſe of them and their Religion for their owne ſafety?</p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But there be ſome <hi>Mild ones</hi> (ſo ſaith our late Libeller) <hi>ſome fiery, ſome dipaſsionat Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the Earle of Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</note> Aunſwer. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> They be euen iuſt ſo many fiery and diſpaſſionat Traytours. J proue it by his owne libell.</p>
               <p>The firſt he concludeth on himſelfe: The ſecond, <hi>the bleſſed Sacrament</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is once more taken to kill his Ma. Counſellour,</hi> the Earle of Salisbury; <hi>fiue good men</hi> of the diſpaſſionat ſort, yet all goe on fire: a blaſt for the King, a <hi>Shot</hi> for his Counſell; and I dare auouch that whatſoeuer hee bee, dare call that a <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> which is onely taken for binding men to ſuch blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21759:28"/>attemptes, is a Traytour, not onely to the King, but euen to Chriſt himſelfe. Is Chriſt a King himſelfe, the Sauiour of the world, become nowadaies a common cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throat of Kings? Swearing to kill all ſuch as Traitor-Catholiques conſpire againſt? No, he will ſtill make ſuch Sacramentes prooue (as before) but as bloudy <hi>Excrements</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their owne heads.</p>
               <p>But becauſe our<note n="*" place="margin">To the Earle of Salisbury.</note> Libeller is come to <hi>Fannes, able to ſeuer the fault of the profeſſor from the prefeſſion it ſelfe,</hi> which he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth wee haue not. To ſhew them plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we can diſtinguiſh <hi>Diſtinguenda,</hi> and ſo not confound <hi>Profeſſorem</hi> &amp; <hi>Profeſſionem</hi> Thus it goeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Profeſſor,</hi> is Traytour <hi>Doctus, Profeſſio</hi> is Traytour <hi>Docens. Profeſſor</hi> is the Veſſell apt to receiue any liquor at the firſt, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio</hi> is the poyſon infecting euery Veſſell which receiueth it. Now Maiſter <hi>Fanner,</hi> where ſaie you the fault is? Is it not in the <hi>Profeſſion?</hi> And ſuch as once ſucke the milk of it, and become at firſt (as you call them) but <hi>Mild ones,</hi> are eaſily made to receiue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21759:28"/>ſtronger foode, and become <hi>fiery ones</hi> for a <hi>blaſt,</hi> or <hi>good men</hi> for a <hi>Shot. Nemo naſcitur artifex;</hi> and ſo <hi>nemo naſcitur, ſed fit, Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus carnifex:</hi> if it were the fault of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or the Profeſſors; why then ſhould we not finde ſome Browniſtes or ſuch other fects, Cut-throats, <hi>Religionis cauſ'a,</hi> as well as Catholikes? No, each ſect hath his own errors,<note place="margin">Omni, foli, &amp; ſemper.</note> but it is onely <hi>Quarto modo proprium</hi> to Catholi-ſchiſme, <hi>To cut downe Kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then (Sir) if there be no meanes to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Treaſon from the profeſſion, nor the Profeſſion from the Profeſſours, of force muſt you Ma: either ſeparate both from you, or let them ſeparate you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world: you muſt either be conuerted, or euerted. No king ſhall be ſure of his Crown, till they be ſure of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>For firſt, <hi>Spaine,</hi> becauſe he is wholly the Popes, he is ſecure of his Crowne: giuing harbory to none that the Pope-hunteth. And what more liberty ought wee to Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Idolaters, then they to vs? They will obey none but Catholique Kinges; Then (Sir) accept you of none, but true Chiſtian
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21759:29"/>Subiects. True, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, for although they will follow the <hi>Leopard</hi> of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Lyon</hi> of <hi>Scotland in Ciuilibus,</hi> yet ſo ſoone as your Ma. ſhall diſplay the Lyon of <hi>Iuda,</hi> there they leaue you diſclaiming your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, they aequiuocate. Since they will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey but <hi>in tanto,</hi> let them goe beyond Seas <hi>in toto. France,</hi> though he bee turned too good Catholike, yet muſt he go to heauen toothleſſe, becauſe he had not fire enough in his Religion, but harboureth ſuch as his holineſſe hunteth. And ere he come thither muſt he paſſe <hi>perpontem amentium,</hi> as in that late treaſon of the mad man on the bridget for it is well ſaid;
<q>
                     <l>Eſt Papa pater Pontifex,</l>
                     <l>Non pontifex, ſed potifex,</l>
                     <l>Non potifex, ſed panifex,</l>
                     <l>Non panifex, ſed carnifex,</l>
                  </q> And becauſe of his Vbiquitarie holineſſe, it encreaſeth thus:
<q>
                     <l>Hic Carnifex, infernifex,</l>
                     <l>Eſt Papapater Pontifex.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Britaine</hi> onely, <hi>Britaine,</hi> becauſe hee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21759:29"/>vſeth calme and chriſtian medicaments for quenching their <hi>Aetnian</hi> conſciences, as the Oyle of Lenity, the Balme of Mercy, the mouth of Propheſie, workes without arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy (the only Phyſick for queaſie ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks ouercharged with the Dregs of that whoriſh cup.) Therefore muſt his Ma. goe to Heauen by a blaſt, and in the workes of his <hi>Supererogation,</hi> his whole poſterity, and almoſt his people with him. And ſo by way of <hi>Aequiuocation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The libeller aforeſaid.</note> 
                  <hi>(They wish him to bee as great a Saint in heanen, as he is a king on earth)</hi> ſo ſhould he be no more a King on earth. And we wiſh them <hi>vniuoce,</hi> and <hi>vna voce,</hi> that they were all preſently as true Saintes in Heauen, as they bee falſe Traytours on Earth: So ſhall they bee as great Saintes as the King; for they are as falſe as hee is great. But heerein prooue they that olde ſpeech true. <hi>Pernicioſa Lenitas, ſalutaris ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three ſortes of Catholiques haue I euer remarked, one youthly;<note place="margin">Lecherous Catholiques.</note> leaning moſt to that Lawe which gaue moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to theyr luſts: <hi>Woundes</hi> and <hi>paſsions,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21759:30"/>Tauerne,</hi> and <hi>Brothel-houſe,</hi> faſt ſo many fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, and all is well.</p>
               <p>Another,<note place="margin">Ignorant Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques.</note> 
                  <hi>Ignorant; de profundis,</hi> and <hi>cor mundum,</hi> knowing as little what they ſay, as what they do. <hi>Ignorantiamater pietatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third,<note place="margin">Treacherous Catholiques.</note> purified Catholiques; the Popes firſt borne, and thoſe are onely for ſhauing of Kings Crownes.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, good lawes may bridle liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and correction breede knowledge. For the ſecond, ſome exorciſmes would bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to, baniſh this ſpirit of darkeneſſe, or elſe they ſent to Rome for exerciſe of their Religion. For the third, whereſoeuer they be found, <hi>Exalt Haman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farre hath my <hi>Bonefire</hi> plaied vpon theſe two points, <hi>Profeſſor</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> apparaling each point, not according to the owne merit, but my owne meanes, all in Truth.</p>
               <p>Now begins my fire from that corner to die (as it were) for a dolefull ſhew, euen pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying, (though it bee afire) that <hi>Seeming piety</hi> ſhould make any Princes Subiects ſo <hi>alienated</hi> from any Prince, much more ſuch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21759:30"/>a princes ſubiects, by a catholike co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Italienated</hi> againſt ſuch a Prince. A Prince (J ſay) to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath giuen (&amp; ſo giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to vs) ſuch qualities, as are not to be expected, but when the courſes of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> come about: for euery King is no more a <hi>Dauid,</hi> then each <hi>Dauid</hi> a King. Yet muſt he haue a blaſt. And whenſoeuer (but O <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ) ſo ſhall be, their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, (but vnremediable) poſterity ſhall worſhip him in his <hi>Tombe,</hi> with whom they wraſtled in his <hi>Throne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is this the onely miſery of our Kingdomes, but euen of all Chriſtiandome; Hence is it that the <hi>Turke</hi> to whom the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name of Chriſt is odious, goeth out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Chriſtendome, not ſo much by his owne force, as ſought vnto, for feare of ſuch Catholique fire, as, where the <hi>Turke</hi> often contenteth himſelfe with<note n="*" place="margin">Bodies.</note> 
                  <hi>Somata,</hi> they wil haue both<note n="*" place="margin">Soules and bodies.</note> 
                  <hi>Somata Pſychas:</hi> for the <hi>Turk</hi> hath not yet learned to <hi>equiuocate,</hi> nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, vntill hee turne Catholique: neither know In ſo much oddes as men talk of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene an ignorant, pittifull, Jnfidell Turk,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21759:31"/>and a wilfull, cruell, Jdolatrous Catholique; beſide, that the Turke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in <hi>Subiugans,</hi> the other <hi>Subditus,</hi> and yet will ſubdue all.</p>
               <p>But leauing that Pittileſſe Turke, to teach theſe pittileſſe Catholiques, we returne to our <hi>Iacob,</hi> both ready and able to hold out the one, and throwe out the other in hys new conquering word: <hi>Put away your ſtrange Gods from amongſt you;</hi> Yea, aſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger God then was either that <hi>Calfe</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> or the <hi>Philiſtimes Dagon,</hi> is this Catholique <hi>Dragon;</hi> who will neuer talke with <hi>Iacob</hi> in other tearmes, then <hi>Blow vp King,</hi> till he <hi>Throw out Catholique,</hi> at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Catholi-ſchiſme: for no <hi>Apelles</hi> ſhall euer ſo perfectly paint out Popery, as it hath pictured it ſelfe in this little blaſt, not in Name but in Nature, not his viſage one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but his workes,<note place="margin">Powder the true picture of Popery.</note> 
                  <hi>Powder,</hi> pourtraying as well the <hi>Mild</hi> as <hi>fiery</hi> Catholiques. Thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Powder</hi> kindled, bloweth vp all: <hi>bot Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. Powder</hi> applyed cold, eateth vp all, J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron or ſteele; <hi>Mild Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Powder, muſt alwayes be vpmoſt, and ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21759:31"/>may it be fiered on the palme of the hand: but if vndermoſt, it bloweth vppe all; So ſtood our Parliament-houſe on the verie Pillars of Popery, Barrels of powder: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would keepe Popery vnder, they ſhould haue all gone vppe. But place once the Pope aboue Prince and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and ſo ſleepe in ſafety.</p>
               <p>Then (Sir) vſe powder, as Powder; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet it by it ſelfe apart, where you may bee ſure of it both from <hi>Firy</hi> blowing or <hi>Mild</hi> rouſting; or if there be no lodging for it, ſend it beyond Seas to the <hi>Netherlandes</hi> whence it came; they haue both more vſe of mines and ſhot, then we. And being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas, I will become ſurety it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer blow vppe any on this ſide, make ſure within who liſt.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe the Carte of <hi>Phoebus Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> ruled by <hi>Pope Phaeton,</hi> drawne by Wilde Ieſuits, and attended by <hi>Catesby, Perſie, Digbies,</hi> all good Catholiques, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling once more on the land, will burne vp <hi>Iacob</hi> with his <hi>Rahell,</hi> his <hi>Ruben,</hi> and hys
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21759:32"/>
                  <hi>Leuits,</hi> the whole Princes and people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. Gather it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogither, leaue not here and there a ſparkle, leſt either <hi>Aeolus</hi> blow, or <hi>Vulcane</hi> beate; &amp; ſo we haue a new blaſt: for the Pope and the Diuell are ſildome at wrath, they be both cunning Aequiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Gather them, not (as they did you) to an vnknowne deſtruction, but either to a hopeleſſe coniunction, or a happy ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let Maieſty ſeat it ſelfe on the Throne of authority, aſſiſted both with Iuſtice and Mercy, and ſo giue them one <hi>Ite, miſſa est,</hi> for all.</p>
               <p>And ſurely it is a ſore perſecution, where the ſeed of Rebellion blowing vp Prince &amp; all, for religion is ſent (for preuention ſake) in peace, to the ſoyle of their owne Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: here it is no fire (J hope.) What craued the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> but<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 5, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>leaue to goe worship in the wilderneſſe?</hi> What craue our poore Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burning in <hi>Spaine</hi> (but for not yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them Religion) more then leaue to retire? But ſuch <hi>Pharaos Ethnicke</hi> and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique (like that<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16, 8</note> 
                  <hi>Steward, wiſe his owne generation</hi>) may teach vs more prouidence in our profeſſion.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21759:32"/>
               <p>Since this Ile was accurſed of the Pope, in our Princes, and ſo caſt in Chriſts handes, Popery hath neuer proſpered here. It ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more falſe and artificiall fire to foſter it then do Oranges, and yet is euen rotten before it be ripe. Elſe where can be Ladies found that can giue the blind their Legges,<note place="margin">Virgo Hallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, and Aſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collis Lipſius.</note> and the lame their eyes; in euery ſtreet cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a Chriſt, and towards <hi>Rome</hi> is Religion ſo ripe, that from euery tree they may pull a <hi>Pope-granat,</hi> a <hi>Pater-garnet: So Ite, miſſa eſt,</hi> is the only beſt both for their ſoules and our bodies.</p>
               <p>But my fire being build for ioy, and now neere ſpent, time it were that our mirthfull <hi>Chorus</hi> went once about it in this order. Our <hi>Iacob,</hi> holding in his one ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the <hi>Nobility</hi> in the other, his <hi>Leuits</hi> and <hi>Cleargy</hi> followeth, or rather cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, the whole body of <hi>Iſraell</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O Iacob Prince of Iſraell, proclaime not, but practiſe a reformation vnto vs: preſerue vs from fire. Iacob</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Put away theſe ſtrange Gods that be amongſt you,</hi> and ſetteth them a worke to ſee to their owne ſafety in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21759:33"/>all time comming. Then Princes of Jſraell, make no more couenants with ſuch Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, whom nothing can bind to <hi>Iacobs god,</hi> nor from whoſe fire nothing can deliuer <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> ſelfe.</p>
               <p>All lyeth on Iacob, for except he preuaile among men, no hope of reformation: for both in Church and Nobility are a kind of ſtrange Gods.</p>
               <p>The Church heere is two-fold (and ſo farewell one-foldneſſe) one ſort is, who can neither be knowne by Coate nor carriage, to be Church-men, but like a pack of wilde Mulets) whoſe nature is, the more they are loaden, the lighter to goe) charged with church liuings, can neuer be ouerburthned with benefices: taking it for the cheef mark of their Chriſtianity, that they haue diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſts coat, and parted his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt them:<note place="margin">Ioſ. 7, 11.</note> Church-men, not of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but ſo called: <hi>Sacrilegious Achans,</hi> who haue not onely ſtolne (in the minority of our gratious King) from the houſe of God things conſecrated, but euen the execrated alſo, the <hi>Babilonish garment,</hi> and the <hi>tongue
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21759:33"/>of gold,</hi> and the portion of <hi>Leui,</hi> thereby ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the golden tongue of Chriſtes Goſpell; but haue alſo made ſuch Lawes, and haue cloathed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with ſuch offices, as may bee able to maintaine them. Theſe <hi>Achans</hi> can ſay in time of neede, <hi>Let the King liue of his owne,</hi> and <hi>puram eleemoſinam</hi> to the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chour. But, prayſed bee GOD, our <hi>Iacob</hi> hath appointed (as did <hi>Ioſua</hi>) <hi>a to morrow</hi> to them, to ſanctify the people, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable thing may bee taken away, and ſo this <hi>their ſtrange God</hi> not onely put from them, but maintenance giuen for planting the true God amongſt them.</p>
               <p>The other ſort is, the Preaching, but not fully priuiledged Church, being abridged of the former, both of liuings and liberties: True Leuits, but a <hi>Strange GOD</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cropen in amongſt them, a ſparkle of the Powder of diuiſion:<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 49, 7. Deut. 10, 8.</note> For where God at firſt diuided them among the reſt of the People, for theyr inſtruction, they bee nowe diuided and at oddes among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to their owne deſtruction; all buſied about white and blacke, while Catholiques
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21759:34"/>carry away ſoules and bodies, in ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies more then ſubſtance, diſputing anent <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> while the other ouerthroweth the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere would our <hi>Iacob</hi> faine haue the <hi>ſtrange God away,</hi> and reſtore the <hi>Leuits</hi> to there former ſtate, onely yet impeded by <hi>Leui,</hi> his diſputes and <hi>Achans</hi> difficulties. God accord the one, and remoue th'other; that, as <hi>Leui</hi> firſt iſſued out of <hi>Iacobs</hi> loines; ſo, our <hi>Leuits</hi> hauing their libertyes reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Iacobs lawes, may with their <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſo ſoundly iumpe &amp; ioyne in the cauſe of religion, that in all his Kingdomes the onely<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 31.53.</note> God of <hi>Abraham</hi> be ſworne by; and not with <hi>Laban,</hi> the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Nahor;</hi> that is, a Papiſt, a Puritan, &amp;c. And his <hi>Leuits</hi> againe (beeing an eſtate of all others ſeated moſt in the harts of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, able in one day, yea, all in one houre weekely, to ſpeake to all the people, which <hi>Iacob</hi> cannot do, may be made the mouth of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Subiectes for knitting their harts vnto him. Heere is both <hi>piety</hi> and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Pollicy, Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Religion, God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21759:34"/>
               <p>The Nobility too much giuen to nouilty; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt running ouer ſtrange Realmes, and ſo bring home <hi>ſtrange Gods.</hi> Some, ſuch refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations as begin at the Kings throat; ſo dyd <hi>Gowry:</hi> others, and too many, a little Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like powder, too ready for a <hi>Blaſts, Shot.</hi> And howſoeuer no man will hold, that ſo ſoone as a man is turned Catholique, he is ſtraight tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Traytor (God forbid) yet (I ſay) hath he ſo ſoone planted in him, that powerfull ſeede of Treaſon, which ſeconded by ſmooth <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries,</hi> doeth by degrees draw him vnto the depth of many deſperate ſins, to which of his owne nature he ſhould neuer haue inclined: firſt perſwading that ſinne is venial; then that ſinne is not ſinne, and laſt that hugeſt ſinnes are higheſt meritorious.</p>
               <p>And though each ſpirit bee not alike deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in daring (becauſe perhaps not alike la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured) yet, if the Moone had changed on vs comforme to their Catholike Calender, as the <hi>fieryones</hi> ſhould haue executed; ſo the <hi>Mild ones</hi> wold haue accepted the common benifit, counting it <hi>bonum,</hi> though not <hi>bene factum.</hi> They had all ſtood for Nouations, a newe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21759:35"/>world, a new King and a new Religion. The <hi>Mild ones</hi> ſerue to harbour the <hi>fiery ones;</hi> one <hi>Miſſa,</hi> is Miſtris to both, both haue one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end, <hi>Tolerations, Alterations,</hi> or (if al faile) <hi>Exterpations.</hi> Away then with all Popery, hot or cold; and God ſtrengthen our <hi>Iacob</hi> to go on in his beginnings<note n="*" place="margin">The laſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly aſsiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the K. at Haly Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</note> before he entred his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> for order taking with the Education of the yong Nobles of his land; chrifly ſuch as ſhould bee ſent beyond Seas, left by ſuch Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Regeneration fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Traditions, the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Treaſons; and vnwritten Verity, maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a counterfeited charity, Princes bee not brought againe to the ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mbles, and the people as Beues for ſacrifices. Thus (ſir) my fire hauing ſpent much of his endles fewel <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> giueth out this one glimps (as his laſt breath) on your own ſacred perſon. That, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you are found to be in Name and life a <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> in Birth right and bleſſings a <hi>Iacob;</hi> in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaus</hi> and Enimies a <hi>Iacob;</hi> in Tentations and Wraſtlings a <hi>Iacob;</hi> and in ſtrength and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailinges a <hi>Iacob:</hi> ſo in dutifull thankfulneſſe you be alſo a <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 35, 1</note> God then biddeth you (as he <hi>bad Iacob</hi>) <hi>ariſe, go vp to Bethel</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnrip in Gods houſe. Then with <hi>Iacob</hi> take with you
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21759:35"/>
                  <hi>your houshold and all that are with you:</hi> and ſo many as will not goe with you to <hi>Bethel</hi> Gods houſe, ſend them to <hi>Bethauen</hi> the Houſe of vanity, the land of their Jdols.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſſe, the moſt part will quite their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols,* and giue <hi>Iacob</hi> their <hi>earings,</hi> the cauſe of their <hi>errings,</hi> which then your H. may hide (as did <hi>Iacob</hi>) <hi>vnder a Oke</hi> of euer laſting obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion. Danger on ſucceſſe, are neither to bee feared; the fear is on their ſide: for no ſtrength in <hi>ſtrange Gods.</hi> You ſee how ſmall a circle can exerciſe their minds; how little a mark raketh vp whole fiue Romiſh Muſketters; euen your Ma. moſt faithfull<note n="*" place="margin">The letter to the Earle of Salisbury.</note> 
                  <hi>Salisbury;</hi> but alaſſe, it is <hi>Virtutem viri non perſonam</hi> they aime at. But howſoeuer, better it were to leaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quering, then dye yeelding; better to repaire Religion decaying, then reſtore it once loſt; better die martyred then onely murthered; and better Vindicate in time our <hi>Iacobs</hi> life; then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge his vntimely death. What if none were to aſſiſt, but he that fought for him at Perth? That informed his minde at our late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament? In the firſt, <hi>Iacob</hi> expected a <hi>Banquet,</hi> not a <hi>Reformation:</hi> in the laſt he intended an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21759:36"/>
                  <hi>Vnion,</hi> not a <hi>Separation.</hi> Sword and fire haue aſſailed, but neuer preuailed, and ſhall that God diſtitute <hi>Iacob</hi> now wraſtling for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Beſides, the whole body of his Subiectes, ready (as <hi>feete</hi>) to carry him; numbers of his Nobles, as <hi>armes</hi> to defend him: his <hi>Leuits,</hi> as the Trumpets of his mouth, at whoſe ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Walles of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iacob,</hi> as did <hi>Iericho</hi> before<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſua. 6.20</note> 
                  <hi>Ioshua.</hi> And among many thinges forſpoken of old of our <hi>Iacob</hi> (from whatſoeuer ſpirit they breathed) hauing now their full performances; this al, ſo was one, <hi>That he shall pull downe the VValles of Rome;</hi> which ſpiritually vnderſtood, may proue (in the power of God) that as in <hi>Rome</hi> Ethnick:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Scaliger.</note> Imperij fuerat Romani Scotia limes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So in</hi> Rome <hi>Catholique</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Romanae fuerit Scot' Anglus origoruing.</l>
                  <l>Amen, without Acquiuocation.</l>
               </q>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21759:36"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
